<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the tender mercies of the living Lord in causing his holy day to spring from on high, in this our age and generation, after a long night of darkness, that for many ages hath covered the earth and people. With a few words, from my own experience, of what I have found and tasted of the goodness of God in that way of the professors to the world esteem dangerous and erroneous; with a testimony, that it is the path of life, although such as are in the snares of death cannot ponder it, until they come to the light that leads to it.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66854</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829046</idno>
  <idno type="VID">33481</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248495636</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217379</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829046</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99829046e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1860:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the tender mercies of the living Lord in causing his holy day to spring from on high, in this our age and generation, after a long night of darkness, that for many ages hath covered the earth and people. With a few words, from my own experience, of what I have found and tasted of the goodness of God in that way of the professors to the world esteem dangerous and erroneous; with a testimony, that it is the path of life, although such as are in the snares of death cannot ponder it, until they come to the light that leads to it.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end by Humphrey Wolrich.</note>
                  <note>Includes one line of errata.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33481:1"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF THE Tender Mercies OF THE Living Lord, In causing his <hi>Holy Day</hi> to Spring from on <hi>High,</hi> in this our <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Generation,</hi> after a long <hi>Night</hi> of <hi>Darkness,</hi> that for many <hi>Ages</hi> hath covered the <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>People.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">With a few Words, from my own Experience, of what I have found and tasted of the Goodness of God in that Way the Professors of the World esteem Dangerous and Erroneous: With a Testimony, that it is the Path of Life, although such as are in the Snares of Death cannot ponder it, until they come to the Light that Leads to it.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends and People every-where throughout the whole World,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the Openings and Issuings-out of that Light and Life, that is not of this World, this is a <hi>visitation,</hi> and <hi>a Salutation of true and vnfained love</hi> to you all, and in the true Light of the <hi>Living,</hi> with which every one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33481:2"/>of you be enlightened, have an ear open to the Lord, that you may hear, when he calls, and what it is he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires at your hands.</p>
            <p>For, Friends, the living and acceptable time for man to do good, and work the Work of God in, is in the Living Fathers hand and time; therefore all the Children (not of the dead and barren womb, but of the living womb of the morning of the day of God, that lasts for ever) that be born of, and put forth by his living Spirit, they do <hi>wait</hi> in the <hi>Light,</hi> (the way of the eternal life, and gate of true wisdom) that shines in their own hearts, to see the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of his hand (who is <hi>Gods Arm,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> his <hi>Battle. ax,</hi> and <hi>Weapon of War,</hi> with which <hi>Paul</hi> and all the holy men fought the <hi>good Fight</hi> withall) and his work therein going on, even him going on Conquering, and to Conquer all his and the Souls Enemies, that so they indeed may become his workmanship, (his House and Temple to dwell in) whose works and wayes be all holy, and perfect for ever, and perfectly effected, and brought to pass in the hearts of all, that be in all things Conformable to the Image of him, whose heavenly will and good pleasure sanctifies throughout both in Soul, Body and Spirit all that be by Him, and the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the day of his holy Power in their Inward Parts made willing to conform thereto, and stand therein, not in the earthly Wisdom, or Image, but in the heavenly.</p>
            <p>But out of this <hi>will</hi> and time before mentioned, all <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>running avails nothing;</hi> for it is nothing worth; and here were all <hi>formales</hi> and <hi>hypocrits</hi> in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges even great Enemies to the Cross of Christ, the life and power of God to salvation; and here was <hi>Cain</hi> with his <hi>Offering;</hi> and <hi>Esau</hi> with his <hi>Tears;</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33481:2"/>all their <hi>Prayers, Offerings,</hi> and <hi>Observation</hi> of those very things God gave in Commandment to be done,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 66.3. <hi>Isa,</hi> 1.</note> and observed throughout their <hi>Generation;</hi> but they being done in their own will and time, (and way they had chosen) and not in the time and will of the Holy Spirit, by which they were first injoyned and Imposed; the Fire of God having not kindled them, nor salted them, but the <hi>strange fire,</hi> that <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> Offered, in whose hearts the Lord was not sanctified, they were <hi>abomination,</hi> and the Lord <hi>abhorred</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Therefore Christ, who did all things well, even alwayes that which pleased the Father, said to his Brethren about his going to the Feast at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> who were in their own wills and time girding themselves, going whither and when they would, <hi>My time is not yet full Come; but your time is alwayes ready.</hi> So, Friends, and People, All be <hi>swift to hear,</hi> and <hi>slow to speak,</hi> until you hear him speak, and see him putting you forth, and going before you; least the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Fools,</hi> that God hath no delight in, be offered. So all that will go in and out at the <hi>true Door</hi> of the <hi>true Sheep</hi> (that hear the <hi>true Voice</hi> of the <hi>True Shepherd</hi> of the soul (the <hi>Ingrafted Word,</hi> that alone is able to save it) and cannot hear the Hirelings) into the living Pasture and springs of Life, they must <hi>wait</hi> for the <hi>Operation</hi> of the hand and power, that opens the Door, and gives entrance thereinto, for the Inheritance that is Incorruptible, is not seen, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, or attained unto by any outward thing; but in, and through that which is Incorruptible, even the single and perfect eye of God, which all the disobedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do close, and so shut themselves out of by their sin, and transgression; and so calls Darkness, that they <hi>walk
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33481:3"/>in Light;</hi> and the Light they being estranged from and out of, they call <hi>Darkness.</hi> And here is the <hi>Truth</hi> of God changed into a lye, and the <hi>Just suffers,</hi> and is Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>unjust,</hi> all-though in it self lives alwayes and is unchangeably a witness against such.</p>
            <p>But all whose minds come to be singly and alone stay'd in the True Light, that doth manifest all evill thoughts and things, which is the <hi>Eye</hi> of God, they come to see God, the Father and holy fountain of that Light (and be satisfied with seeing) which is the Saints Inheritance, to whom they be gathered, and gathering by that same that shines in the heart, first Convincing of sin, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and manifesting evil thoughts and deeds in their first rise. When the enemie put them into the mind and heart, then will this quench them all, if believed in; it will become the <hi>whole armour of God</hi> for every part, as it is taken unto, and stood in; it shews <hi>good thoughts</hi> and <hi>deeds</hi> also, and their root from whence they spring; and it doth lead into <hi>all good,</hi> that God doth require of us; and out of all <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> which the letter could never do them that call it their <hi>best Rule,</hi> and so think (like the deceived <hi>Jews</hi>) to have <hi>eternal Life</hi> therein; which <hi>Rule</hi> they can wrest any way to plead for the <hi>evil practices,</hi> and <hi>dead formes</hi> they live in, which the <hi>Living Spirit</hi> they cannot do. And this <hi>Holy Weapon</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, is able to bring down every <hi>high Thought, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination</hi> and thing that hath been, or shall be at any time exalted above that of God in the Temple of God, this is of <hi>a drawing nature</hi> out of <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> saith <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.11. of a <hi>teaching nature</hi> to deny all that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like God; it doth the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>God</hi> he sends it to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish; it as naturally <hi>draws</hi> towards God and <hi>good things,</hi> and in the heart begets <hi>pure desires</hi> and <hi>thoughts</hi> after <hi>God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33481:3"/>holiness</hi> and <hi>purity</hi> as doth the Stone, that is in the Air, fall downward, and here is the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>a man</hi> that looks upward to heavenly things, and that of the <hi>beast,</hi> that looks downward into the <hi>earthly</hi> and <hi>visible</hi> things, seen and made manifest, glory to the holy Father for ever. This in all things, words and works the Creature doth speak, or do, calls for <hi>circumspection, humility</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> in this Light or Grace that brings Salvation, and to all men hath appeared, is the <hi>hidden Wisdom,</hi> even the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den wisdom, that God ordained to be his saints glory obtained of God; in it whoever asks and seeks, <hi>receives and finds,</hi> and who in the obedience to it, and denial of self, and selfish ways and wisdom in it waits in humility, comes to be <hi>taught</hi> of the Lord, and knows the living Shepherd as did <hi>David,</hi> and all the true Sheep of his Pasture; they also feel the Issues of that Life the World knows not, nor sees not, whose cry is, <hi>There's no being free from sin in this Life,</hi> in their own hearts do they feel it Issuing out to <hi>take away sin;</hi> and in him, nor in his Life and Light, whom the World knows not (even the Spirit of Truth) in him there is no sin; but in the Covenant with Death and Hell there is not perfection nor freedom from sin, in that life there is not; as they that have made an agreement there-with, and be therein, do say, and can see no otherwise, because Darkness hath blinded their eyes. But this is not the everlasting Covenant that God makes with his Children; for it must be broken and disannulled.</p>
            <p>But all that be in Christ, the everlasting Covenant, the new Life, and Covenant in whom is no sin, do witness another thing, even the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> that is in him, in whom is <hi>no sin,</hi> the covenant that God will never change, nor alter, for it set all that in it abide, free
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33481:4"/>from the Law of sin, and so from the covenant of death that entered by sin; and the agreement the soul had made with it, is now broken; the Darkness is past, and the true Light comes; Old things be done away, all things are become new; the Old Man put off with his Deeds, and the new Man that's heavenly, put on, and he sets the heart and mind on heavenly things: and so, as in the First Adam all dye, death passeth over them, the effect and wages of their sin, so in Christ the Second Adam the Lord from Heaven are all made alive: for he is the shepherd, and living Stone of <hi>Israel;</hi> to whom we coming in the Faith and obedience as to a living Stone, and in him abide, we of his Life and Heavenly Vertue do receive, and so become living Stones, also elect and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, being prepared to build him an house to dwell in, we grow into an Holy Temple in the Lord; for <hi>the place of my Rest, and the place of the Soals of my Feet is Holy,</hi> saith the Lord God. And in him even the true Light, who ever abids, sins not; for he only leads in the way of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, but never did he lead any one into Sin. So such as be led by him, set to their seal, that he is the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginner and the finisher of the good work, and creation of God in the heart, the Spirit by which we call, and cry <hi>Abba Father;</hi> the Saviour of the soul; the Ingrafted Word that alone is able to do it; stronger then the <hi>Devil,</hi> for he binds him, and limits him and dispossesseth him, and all his Servants wrath and malice doth he restrain, but what shall praise him: by him God made all things, and he upholds all things, he created the Mountains and formed the winds, he tells men and women all they have done amiss from their youth; he doth the work that no other man doth; and is not this the very Christ,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33481:4"/>the <hi>Immanuel, God with us;</hi> the true light that lighteth all men: in his light God dwells, and puts it on as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ever; the Spiritual Tent and Tabernacle he hath pitched in the Sons of men; the lively, and living Oracle, at which all the Sons and Daughters of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God do ask counsel; by and through whom to God the Father of all be praises &amp; glory given in the Church, World without end, for all his great goodness in, and through Christ, this true Light, received; he alone is God over all, and above all, whose mercy endures for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>O FRIENDS, stay not in any thing, that the Light calls out of; for that is to stay in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi> Reason not, and consult not with flesh and Blood, as did the <hi>evil Spies,</hi> who believed not the words of the Lord, but swaryed aside, like <hi>a Deceitful Bow,</hi> and in their hearts turned back again into <hi>Egypt,</hi> when they brought up a Slander on the <hi>Good Land,</hi> and made the hearts of their brethren to fail by <hi>turning back</hi> into the pernicious way of ungodly men. But be of the number of them that believe: And in <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joshua</hi>'s Spirit, who wholy followed the Lord God of <hi>Israel,</hi> go ye on hoping all things, and believing all things, bearing all things (but that which is evil) that so the soul may be saved out of all its enemies hands in Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and holiness to serve, praise, and glorifie the Lord always. For God is drawing the heart and affections cleen out of all <hi>visible transitory</hi> and <hi>fading things</hi> to himself, the one thing, that him it may affect, and cleave unto in all things, who is the Fulness, the staff and Goodness of them all.</p>
            <p>O Friends, that every one of us may say to the Lord,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33481:5"/>as did <hi>David,</hi> and not lye, <hi>I have Intreated thy Favour with my whole heart;</hi> not with a part of it, but with my <hi>whole</hi> heart. O happy thing, when one draws nigh to the Calls of the Grave, that one can say with good <hi>Hezekiah, O Lord, thou knowest, I have walked before thee with a perfect heart, and have done that which is Right in thy Sight.</hi> This Testimony in our bosom is better to do one good, then all Testimonies without can be to do one harm.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> in the Light of God is the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and the way of <hi>Death</hi> set before you: O do not stand at the parting of the ways, at the head of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Field, consulting with Images (like as the King of <hi>Babilon</hi> did) for there will the Enemy <hi>divine</hi> a Lye unto you; but come into the way of Life: that so the <hi>Refiner</hi> and <hi>Fuller</hi> may purge you, and make you white.</p>
            <p>But Friends, all hear this word, and let it sink down into your hearts: When the Innocent Spirit and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God moves to do any thing, and the way thou shouldest walk in, and the work thou shouldst do, clearly set before thee, then the Enemy (that is always ready, if not watched against) catcheth the mind, and turns it aside into the reasoning, there to feed upon the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> that devours the <hi>Life.</hi> For in that <hi>knowing mind</hi> death raigns, but in the <hi>Innocency</hi> (that is in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and subjection to the heavenly will) <hi>Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortallity is brought to Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the word of Truth it self to <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> that that which opens the <hi>understanding,</hi> may be dwelt in. For the Lord, who by wisdom created the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the Earth, the Seas and Fountains of waters, he it is that giveth wisdom to all, who in fear wait on him for it. Out of his mouth cometh the <hi>good understanding,</hi> and his breath, as a stream of Fire sweeps away and burns
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33481:5"/>up all that which hath darkened it, and given man the <hi>bad understanding,</hi> which the <hi>appearance</hi> of God in the heart by his <hi>Spirit of Judgment</hi> and <hi>Burning,</hi> and the <hi>Issuings out</hi> of his <hi>Life</hi> therein doth confound and bring to nought. So, <hi>True Judgment</hi> in the heart and soul of man to be set up, is <hi>a gift</hi> from the throne of the holy Lord God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom nothing can stand out of his own <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> that sits upon the throne, because of the <hi>Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the <hi>Spots</hi> and the <hi>Blemishes,</hi> that be in them, which in Christ <hi>the Light (and Life)</hi> of men, <hi>in whom is no Spot,</hi> be all done away: and to have him, is the sum of all shaddowes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scripture mentions</hi> the <hi>true Minister,</hi> Christ in the <hi>Inner parts,</hi> as he ministers to you out of his fulness free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, so to others, as from him we freely do receive, ought we freely to minister as <hi>good stewards</hi> of the manifold <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> of God. And here be all <hi>Men-made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> that be made by <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>outward Learning</hi> in mans will and time, all excluded and denyed. When the voyce of the <hi>true Shepherd</hi> is heard and followed; then not the <hi>Hirelings</hi> heard or followed any longer. And here was, and still is the ground and cause of all <hi>differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> between the <hi>true Prophets</hi> and Ministers, and the <hi>false.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> had their Way and Work in the <hi>Living Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> wherein they were workers together with God, and Christ, that sent them, and put them forth; and their <hi>wonds</hi> they received in the eternal Word and Spirit of Holiness: they were <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and were a <hi>Savour of Life</hi> to the life in all; but especially to them, that had an ear open to hear the spirit. But the <hi>other</hi> had their way in the <hi>Imaginations,</hi> and their work in the <hi>Letter,</hi> and in the <hi>death,</hi> that had heard the fame of life, but knows not the place of it.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33481:6"/>And here is the ground of <hi>Persecution,</hi> the Root and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the <hi>World turned upside down,</hi> which neither knows, nor receives the things that be of the spirit of God; for to it they be <hi>Foolishness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thanks be to God; over it all is the <hi>Holy One</hi> risen, who doth not leave the Soul in hell, or in the horrible pit amongst the condemned ones. For <hi>Life</hi> hath broke the bands of Death, and swallowed it up in victory. And this <hi>Corruptible</hi> and <hi>Mortal</hi> puts on <hi>Incorruption</hi> and <hi>Immortality</hi> to the joy of the Immortal Soul, that is not left in Hell; but doth rejoyce and glory in God for the Opening of this <hi>bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and holy Mystery,</hi> that is hidden from the <hi>Fleshly</hi> and <hi>Foolish Wisdom</hi> of Man, which is very busie about it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Friends,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MY heart is filled with Thankfulness to the Lord for all his Mercy, and Favour, and Benefits, that freely he hath bestowed upon me without any cause or ground on my part, but because mercy towards the objects of mercy pleaseth him. O let me not forget them forever, but amongst his heavenly Host and Redeemed Ones in the midst of the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>First-born,</hi> that have the living Record in themselves, and their Names written in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, amongst them all let me sing Praises to our God for his living and sure Mercies, that endures forever, even to them that remember his Covenant, the Precepts, Statuts, and Judgments and the Commandments of his Mouth, so as to do them.</p>
            <p>But O the Blindness of the World, its Priests and People, that say, The Lords Voice is not heard now adays; that Revelation and Inspiration is ceased: These be Witnesses all of them against themselves, that they know not the Father, that they Night, and the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33481:6"/>of Darkness is come upon them, in which they grope like Blind Men, even as indeed they be, as the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Effect of Gods hand against them for their Rebellion and Opposition of that holy and heavenly Light of Christ, that the Despised People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> have born witness to, that in the Hearts of men and women it doth shine showing, and manifesting to them the secret Thoughts and Intents therein, and allthough Darkness and thick Clouds be about it by reason of the Rebellion thereto, and mans not Walking in it as he ought, for which End God hath given it even to be his Way, Governour &amp; Guide in all things, but walkes in the Darkness and evil Thoughts, and Deeds, that he loves rather; and yet from its Reprofes man cannot hide himself, nor go any where wholy from it, because it possesses his Reins, as <hi>David</hi> saith, Psalm 139. For it is the Eye that sees every Secret Thing, and Heavens Light, that reveals mans Iniquity, and shews man, that he is a Sinner, and so short of Gods Glory, and perfect Peace, which this Light that shines in the heart, gives the Light of the Knowledg of: it is the Gate, in which God doth open his Mouth, and his Servants open their Mouths. But man, that doth not wait at it, he hears not his Voice, although he Speak once and again, man perceaves it not; and so he being in the Dark, condemns them that be in the Light, who hear his Voice, and see his Countenance, which he cannot in the Dark fathom, nor comprehend, and their words, that spoke from the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Word, as in them it moves, and opens, and brings out the Deep Things o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, they be counted Dangerous, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, &amp; even Blasphemy, as in Ages past they were by the same Spirit and Seed of evil-Doers, that shall never be so renowned, as to know them; for from it God in his Wisdom hath hidden these Deep Things; and indeed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33481:7"/>they be Foolishness to that Spirit, and so it is said in the Holy Writings, <hi>Wisdom is too high for a Fool.</hi> But blessed be the Lord and magnified, and extolled very high be his worthy and Reverent Name above all Names and Things for ever, whose Glorious Day is risen, and hath shined and sprung from on high in the Hearts of Thousands to the joy of their Souls and Spirits, which the Resurrection of make willing to follow the Lord, who is the Father, and holy Fountain, from whence it comes; to whom be <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for ever, whose Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion is an Everlasting Dominion, and whose Kingdom Rules over all.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Humphrey Wolrich.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 8. Line 4. for <hi>Calls</hi> read <hi>Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33481:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>